First of all, the male owner of the household has some issues.
其实首先是这个男的男主人就有一点问题
He often speaks in a mournful voice to the old sign.
经常去哭丧的那个声音去跟老牌子说话
This has led to his wife yelling as well.
然后弄得他们家是他老婆也吼的
My son also yells
儿子也吼
He yells himself too
他自己也吼啊
It's really terrifying
非常的可怕
And recently, it's gotten even more unbearable
然后最近呢又更恶心了一点呢
The tenth floor is under renovation
就是十楼正在装修
When they do the renovation
他装修呢来来讲的话
Sometimes on Saturdays and Sundays, they work a bit
有时候周6日呢要小赚
During the usual nap time from ten to two in the afternoon
那么一下正常的午休的十点到两点中间呢
They don't always stick to the schedule
他有时候也不是特别的遵守时间
This really gets me annoyed.
这就让我弄得很恼火哈
Then I shared this with some of my friends.
然后我把这个事情跟我的一些朋友分享的人
Some said, 'Oh!',
有人就说哎呀
You should call the police.
你应该打电话报警啊
His first reaction was that you should report it to the police.
啊他的反应就是第一这事就报警
Someone suggested you could move out.
有人说你可以搬家呀
Others said you could confront them directly.
有人说你什么你可以上门理论啊
All these suggestions are telling you how to resolve the current conflict.
就是所有的这些东西都在告诉你如何解决目前的这个矛盾啊
But the difference between people lies in their mindset. The way of thinking about problems is different. We often say that many people are poor because they are poor. It's not because of laziness, but because there's a problem with their way of thinking.
但是其实人与人之间的差别就是在于思想啊 思想思考问题的方式不一样 我们常说其实人很多人穷之所以穷 并不是因为懒惰 而是因为思维的方式出了问题啊
The thinking patterns of the rich and the poor have fundamental differences.
富人跟穷人的思维方式有根本性的区别
So, how should you approach thinking about this issue?
就是说你在该怎么样去思考这件事呢
Actually, this is a good thing.
就是说其实这是一件好事啊
Right now, my main task is to stay at home and sleep.
你看我现在主要的任务就是在家呆着睡觉啊
And then to make videos.
然后就是拍视频
The most important thing when it comes to shooting videos is to go out and shoot.
拍视频最重要的来讲的话就是要出去拍啊
Going out to shoot is what makes it a VLOG.
出去拍这东西才是VLOG
This actually encourages me to get more exercise during the day.
其实这就促使了我在白天的时候呢多出去运动
Everyone knows that getting out and exercising is beneficial for me.
大家也知道出去了运动来讲对我来讲是有好处的
Whether it's going out to shoot videos,
无论是出去拍摄
it's good for my career,
是对事业有好处
or going out to exercise,
还是出去运动啊
it's good for my health,
对身体有好处啊
getting out there is always better than staying at home.
都是走出去都是比待在家里强
So, when people argue or the upstairs neighbors are renovating,
所以这个东西别人吵架和楼上装修啊
these are ways that nature is waking you up,
这个都是老天爷唤醒你
encouraging you to step out.
让你往出走的一种方式
Speaking of crisis,
所谓危机危机啊
in times of danger, there are often opportunities as well. Typically, danger and opportunity coexist. Just like the Chu-Han Contention between Liu Bang and Xiang Yu, many times, the more there is an opportunity.
在危险的时候呢 通常还有机会啊 通常危危险与机会是并存的啊 就好像刘邦与项羽的这个楚汉战争一样 很多的时候就是越是有机会
The more there are opportunities for action,
越是有战机的时候
the more fleeting those chances are,
那个一纵即逝的机会
you must seize them to turn your life around.
你要抓住了就翻身了
So we say that for the poor to improve their situation,
所以我们说穷人想翻身
the most crucial thing is to seize opportunities.
最重要的就是要抓住机会
You have to be willing to take risks.
就得敢冒险
But what does school education teach you?
但是学校教育教给你的是什么呢
School education teaches you to follow the rules.
学校教育教给你是守规矩
But we do say that you should abide by the law.
但是我们说要遵守法律啊
The laws of the country must be followed.
国家的法律要遵守
We must respect the authority of the law.
要尊重法律的权威啊
It’s important to understand that the law treats everyone equally.
要知道这个法律是人人对人人都平等的
Moreover, the penalties for breaking the law are very severe.
而且法律的那惩罚啊非常的严格
You will have to pay a significant social price.
你要付出极大的社会代价
However, you should also understand many unwritten rules between people.
但是同时你要明白人与人之间的很多规矩
There are some you don’t need to follow.
你是没必要守的啊
The poorer you are, the less you should adhere to these rules.
人越穷越不要守规矩啊
There are certain rules that shouldn’t be followed.
不能守的一些规矩
Don't be too concerned about face
不能好面子
Don't stick to the rules too rigidly
不能守规矩
Don't always worry about what others think
不能老是去在乎别人的看法啊
Today, I had a discussion with another UPloader
今天我一个跟另外一个up主
Just because of this, we ended up arguing
就因为这个我就跟他就争起来了
He's had a particularly tough fate
他就是命运特别的多舛啊
He's been extremely unlucky
特别倒霉的一个人啊
From a young age, he's endured a lot of hardship So our life experiences are completely different I had a fairly happy childhood. But that's my own conclusion. Now when I look back on my childhood, I feel that it was quite happy.
从小来讲的话就受了很多罪 所以我们俩的人生体验完全不一样啊 我是属于呃童年比较幸福的 但是这也我自己总结 我现在回视我的回望我的童年 我觉得我童年比较幸福
But like any child, I had my share of troubles.
但是小时候一样有小时候的苦恼啊
Like being bullied by teachers or something like that.
学校老师欺负你或者怎么样啊
Or being bullied by classmates and other such things.
同学欺负你这些各种各样的事情啊
These memories come back.
都会回想
But when you reflect on them,
但是你回想的时候
You'll find
你会发现
that sometimes other classmates might think differently from you
其实有的时候别的同学回想的跟你不一样啊
Oh, other classmates might recall being bullied by you
呵别的同学想的可能是被你欺负的那种经历
So it's completely different
所以是完完全全不一样的
So when people reminisce
所以人他在回忆当中
they tend to romanticize certain aspects
他会美化一些部分
and overlook others
他会忽略一些啊
the parts where they were the perpetrator
自己是这个加害者的部分
Actually, this is quite interesting
其实这个挺有意思啊
Humans have selective memory.
人是一种选择性记忆
But the main issue we're discussing today is that you shouldn't be afraid of what others think of you.
但我们今天讲的主要的问题就是你不能害怕别人是怎么看你的
Or what they say about you.
别人是怎么说你的
And most of the rules in society.
还有这个社会的大部分的规矩啊
I often post more than five statuses a day on my social media.
我经常会一天发五条以上朋友圈
A friend of mine said that anyone who posts more than five statuses a day must be crazy.
我这个朋友就说一天发五条朋友圈以上的人都是精神病
I said, 'I am indeed crazy.'
我说我的确是精神病啊
And anxious.
还有惊恐啊
And also obsessive.
然后还有强迫啊
These all fall under the category of control issues.
这些都是一种啊控制范围啊
It's about the intensity of control.
这个控制强度的问题
What is anxiety? I worry about things far into the future. What is panic? I panic about whether I might have an accident right now. Don't go away. Don't joke with me. That's why I can't control myself in the elevator.
焦虑是什么呢 我会焦虑很远的事情啊 我惊恐是什么呢 我会会为当下会不会窜稀感觉到惊恐啊 你别别开 别跟我开玩笑 就说我之所以能在电梯里喷屎
Actually, it has a lot to do with panic attacks.
其实跟这个惊恐又发作有很大的关系啊
And then there are compulsive behaviors.
然后呢就是强迫行为啊
Like buying things in pairs.
喜欢成双成对的买东西啊
If I like something, I tend to collect the whole set.
喜欢就把一个东西收集齐了
So when it comes to consumerism, this is an issue.
所以其实在面对消费主义这种问题的时候
I actually try to resist this tendency.
我其实是在努力在对抗这种倾向
I am prone to buying more than I need.
其实我本身是容易多买东西的人
So, when it comes to anything,
所以任何东西来讲
it's all related.
它都是与啊
How to talk about the coexistence of V and the machine
怎么说V与机并存的
So we can't emphasize one part
所以不能说去啊强调一个部分
while neglecting the other
你就忽视了另一个部分
In many cases
很多的时候来讲
the fleeting opportunities you have
我们说你之所以有转瞬即逝的这种机会来讲的话
most of the time
其实更多的时候来讲
it's about taking risks at critical moments
就是你要在关键时刻要冒险
so to be able to take risks at critical moments
所以为了关键时刻你能够冒险
you can't afford to be in debt at those critical times
所以关键时刻呢你就不能欠债
There must be a way out.
就不能有没有办法出去啊
The timing for a decisive move.
全力一搏的这个时机
We lack the conditions for a decisive move.
没有办法全力一搏的这个条件
So we need to create those conditions.
所以要创造这种条件
In fact, most of our lives are spent waiting. There are only a couple of days. Only a few opportunities. We need to go all out. How should I put it? Like an arrow released from a bow, aim straight for the bullseye.
我们其实人生中大部分时间都是在等待啊 只有那么一两天 只有那么一两次机会 我们是要全力以赴啊 是要那个怎么说呢 啊像离心的箭一样去正中靶心
So I often say that opportunities to change one's fate come six times a day.
所以来讲我常说这个人生改变命运的机会呢啊每天都有六次
But there's a catch.
但是呢又有一个语病
I mean, the truly significant opportunities to change one's life
就是说人生真正改变命运的大的机会呢
probably only come three times in a lifetime.
一辈子大概有三次
Similarly, the chances to become wealthy also come about three times in a lifetime.
那么说发财的机会一辈子大概是三次
If you can nail all three jumps,
三级跳都做好了
you'll be amazing.
你就厉害了
So, speaking of recent developments,
所以我最近现在来讲
I feel that my Bilibili content is getting increasingly challenging to produce.
我感觉我B站做的有点越来越吃力了
But while it’s challenging,
但是吃力的同时
I realize that everything is a matter of trade-offs.
我感觉到任何东西他都是在此消彼长当中
Perhaps one day my Bilibili content won’t be as good,
也许我B站有一天做的不太好了
but I’ve managed to build up my YouTube channel.
我YOUTUBE都做下来了
Maybe I’m not putting as much effort into social media,
也许我在自媒体这方面发力不是很厉害
but
来讲
perhaps other ventures are taking off.
也许我别的事业都起来了啊
Because right now, I actually have a lot of ideas in my head.
因为我现在其实脑子里构想的
If I were to start from now
我如果要是从现在开始
and stop making videos in the future
如果就不做视频了以后
what should I do?
我应该干什么啊
After careful consideration this time
我这次自己仔细想了以后
I think I should continue with my consulting work
其实我应该继续做我的呃咨询类的工作
especially given the current market environment in China
而特别是现在面对中国的这么一个市场环境下来讲的话
we talk about so many in the world
咱们说世界上有那么多啊
who desperately need to be saved who desperately need to hear the right advice That is, this kind of mental abuse in China the longer this environment persists
急需要被拯救 急需要听到一个正确建议的这么一种需求 也就是说中国的这种自然的这种精神虐待 这种环境越长久啊
the more mentally unstable individuals it creates
创造的精神不正常的人就越多
the more mentally unstable people it produces
创造精神不正常的人越多啊
In many cases
很多的时候来讲
I feel that when it comes to mental treatment, how should I put it
我觉得在精神治疗与这个这个怎么说呢
the normal ones rely on medication
正常的靠自己吃药
on their own strength
自己扛的
there's a huge gap in between
中间有一个非常大的鸿沟
What we call a support group
就是所谓的support group啊
A support group is really important
support group这个东西很重要
A support group
支援小组啊
A support group is crucial when you have stomach issues
支援小组织是在你胃病啊
It's a vital component in preventing mental health disorders
预防精神类疾病的时候非常重要的一个东西啊
I suddenly feel that this area will see growth in the future
突然我觉得这个东西其实是未来我觉得事业业务会增长的一块
Right here
就是在这啊
On one hand, there's a need for regular mental health prevention, treatment, and medication
一方面是需要正常的这种精神类的这个预防和这个治疗和这个开药
The regular
这个正常
Now, the functions of hospitals are mainly focused on maintaining these conditions.
现在医院的机能都是在维持这些东西
However, many people are actually unaware that they suffer from mental illnesses.
但是有很多人其实并不知道自己罹患了精神类疾病啊
Or, to put it another way,
或者来讲的话
they need guidance on how to move forward in life.
他人生需要指导他需要怎么样啊
For example, they need guidance on their path forward, such as career choices, and often in their marital life as well, parents may not always be a reliable source of support, this source that sustains them. You wouldn't turn to your wife
比如说呃前进路上需要指导 比如说他的择业方面需要指导 他的婚姻方面需要很多的时候来讲 父母并不是可靠的 这个知这个支撑他的源头啊 你向你的妻子
or your husband for help either
向你的丈夫求助也不现实
So, in society, people are often left to fend for themselves
所以其实人在社会上通常来讲是孤立无援的
That's why people like us exist
所以为什么才会有我们这种人的存在啊
The existence of people like us
所以我们这种人的存在本身来讲啊
fills a gap in society
他是填补社会的一个空缺
So today, we need to consider this issue
所以我们今天就要想到一个问题了
Whenever there's a void in anything
任何东西它出现空缺以后
there will be a force that fills it
就会有东西有力量会去填补它
Everything that appears to be dangerous in society
所有的在这社会中看似是危险的东西
or seems unreasonable
看似是不合理的东西
is actually a new point of economic growth
实际都是一个新的经济增长点
or a new business model that can fill a gap
或者新的一个业务可以填充的模式
or anything that looks dangerous
或者任何看起来是危险的东西
is actually an opportunity to make money
实际上都是赚钱的机会
it's all about this
就是在于这
so many times
所以很多的时候来讲
we see a societal need starting to emerge here
我们看到一个社会的需求在这儿开始
It develops a wound
它出现伤口
It starts to bleed
开始出现流血
From a personal perspective
你会发现从个人的角度来讲
This is a pain that lingers throughout one's life
这是人一生之痛
But from a societal perspective
但是从社会的角度来讲
This becomes a significant factor that slows down social efficiency
这个就是拖慢社会效率的一个重大的因素
A flaw
一个漏洞
So to speak
所以来讲的话
Someone creates a hole in society Someone has to fix this hole. So this is what I think about my future, in case I decide to stop doing this one day. If it comes to self-media, there might be an impulse and plan to do so. But overall,
有人去把这个社会捅出窟窿 就得有人去修补这个窟窿 所以这就是我对未来可能啊哪天不干了事情的话不干了 自媒体的话可能会有这方面的冲动跟打算 但是总体来讲的话
society has this demand.
社会有这种需求
If not you, Zhang San, then Li Si will do it.
不会是你张三也是会李四会去干这件事情
It's precisely because Chinese parents create so many black holes in the spiritual realm,
正是因为中国式家长会创造出来这么多的精神上的黑洞
that there will be people to fill these black holes.
所以来讲才会有人去填补这个黑洞
That's why there are people teaching you how to avoid pitfalls.
所以才有人去教你怎么避坑
So you see, my books are really selling quite well.
所以你看我的书卖的真的是非常不错啊
I've also drawn two more to give away during the lottery.
我现在抽奖的时候又抽了两本给大家拿出来
This is specifically for the raffle.
专门就来伴奏抽奖
And if this has helped you in any way,
然后如果这个东西对你的人生有帮助的话呢
please leave more positive reviews on our store page.
请你在这个我们的那个店铺在下面呢多留好评啊
It’s great to have more comments.
多发言挺好的
Well, no matter how you look at it,
呃其实无论怎么样来讲的话
instead of always trying to avoid difficulties,
我们就是说你与其去永远的想去避开困难
trying to avoid the breaking points
想去避开爆发点
If you want to avoid these disasters in life,
想去避开人生中的这些灾难的话
the truth is, you can't really avoid them.
其实避是避不开的
More often, it's about taking an active approach to face them,
更多的来讲也用用于学校一种主动迎击
actively managing them,
主动管控
risk management,
风险管控
and even embracing a spirit of adventure.
甚至去冒险的这么一种态度
In other words, life is a mix of good and bad times, it's actually a simple logic. But this logic often tells us why ordinary people shouldn't take risks. Don't take the risk of starting a business Don't take the risk Go for the risk
也就是说人生在世顺手逆曲 其实就是这么一个简单的逻辑 但是这种逻辑背后通常告诉你是为什么普通人不要去冒险啊 不要去冒险创业 不要去冒险 干这冒险干
This is because people can't manage their own risks
这个是因为人没法管控自己的风险
For many people
很多人来讲的话
Especially those who are suppressed at the bottom
特别是压制在底层的人
Many people are very afraid of taking risks
很多人是非常害怕冒险的
But their economic behavior is contradictory
但与他们的经济行为是相反的
They themselves are afraid of taking risks
就是说自己本身害怕冒险
But they buy things on installment plans.
但是却却分期去买东西啊
They are afraid of taking risks themselves.
自己本身害怕冒险
Yet they take out high-interest loans.
却去借高利贷啊
Yet they use services like Meituan Monthly Payment.
却去弄什么美团月付
Things like JD White Card, these hidden high-interest loans are extremely serious.
什么京东白条这种隐形的高利贷是非常非常严重的
For many people,
很多人来讲的话
Huabei means owing tens of thousands of yuan every day.
花呗每天就是欠这个几万块钱
It's often the case.
经常是啊
Well, how to put it?
怎么说呢
His family won't cover his expenses either.
家里边也不会帮他付自己的工资
That would be just a drop in the bucket.
那又杯水车薪
So over time, these financial derivatives,
所以长期以来这些金融衍生品
these financial products,
这些金融的啊
the so-called financial reforms,
所谓的金融改革
are essentially just high-interest loans from ancient times,
就是其实就是古代的高利贷啊
which used to prey on tenants with compounding interest,
现在利滚利之前是吃佃户
now they prey on office workers.
现在是吃上班族
It's just that simple. So it's not some groundbreaking innovation. Who gives these financial products their value? It's the wealthy who pay for them. Right. Who pockets this profit? Well, it's those big shots in finance who create these products.
就是这么简单的东西 所以不是什么创新啊 这些东西这些金融产品谁给他赋的能呢啊都是有钱人给你付的 能 谁去赚走这部分利润呢 啊也就是这些创造金融产品的这些金融界的这些大亨们
They're making money off ordinary people.
他们在赚普通人的钱
So it's just a simple concept.
所以就是这么一个简单的东西
Why am I telling you this?
我为什么会给你讲这些东西
That's because there are many things
是因为很多东西来讲
that he doesn't hear in the school system or in your family
他在学校系统或者在你的家庭系统中听不到
which is why it's called avoiding pitfalls
所以才叫避坑
to steer clear of these
避开这些啊
traps set by the wealthy
有钱人给你挖的坑
Actually
其实来讲
the gap between the rich and the average person is growing wider
现在有钱人跟普通人之间的鸿沟是越来越大了
How to put it
因为这个怎么说呢
with urban development
城市化发展啊
As our country gradually becomes a middle-developed nation,
咱们国家现在逐渐变成一个中等发达国家的时候
you'll notice that many challenges arise,
你会发现很多东西都是面临的啊
the routine growth rate slows down,
日常的常态化增长的速度放缓
and we're starting to experience the ailments of developed countries.
咱们现在也开始有了发达国家的病了啊
So, to put it this way,
所以说来讲的话
finance can be a source of evil,
金融这东西是可以存在之恶
its existence has made many people wealthy,
他的存在呢是让很多人获得了财富
and it has also indirectly helped many others gain wealth,
他的存在人也让很多人帮助间接获得了财富
the distribution of wealth is certainly consistent.
财富的分配是肯定是一致的啊
This thing has made money off you. It's raking in the profits. If Ant Financial can go public and do all sorts of things, then other places are bound to suffer. Right? All the internet financial products you see as great, have countless people bearing the brunt behind the scenes.
这个东西从你这儿赚到了钱 赚的盆满钵满啊 蚂蚁金服能上市能怎么怎么着 那别的地方肯定就是要惨 对不对 所有的你看得非常好的互联网金融产品 背后都是有无数的人在背这个坑啊
So, who is bearing the brunt?
所以谁在背这个坑呢
A large number of left-behind children.
大量的留守儿童
A large number of Generation Z
大量的零零后
Millennials
九零后
many people are in debt
大量的人在负债
so when we talk about it
所以来讲的话
sometimes we have to fill this gap
有时候必须要填上这个坑
if we can't fill this gap
如果填不上这个坑
I'll be filling this bottomless pit
我去填这个无底洞
then we can only avoid this pit
那就只能避开这个坑
that's why I named this book 'Avoiding the Pit'
所以为什么我把这书起名叫做避坑呢
There are some abysses that you can't see.
就是有些深渊你是看不见的
And it's designed to make people fall into these unseen abysses.
而这种深渊让人掉下去才是他的设计目的所在
So, to put it this way,
所以来讲的话
as someone who can't fall in,
作为一个掉不下去的人
or as someone who knows how they design these traps,
或者说作为一个知道他们是怎么设计这些坑的人啊
to put it this way,
来讲的话
I'll be standing right next to your ear,
我就是站在你耳边
only able to give you a single warning,
只能提醒你一句
I can't set up warning signs for you.
我不能给你设置啊警示牌
Then tell you not to go there
然后告诉你不要往那里边走
I can only talk to those who are willing to listen
我只能在能愿意听我说这些话的人呢
whisper softly in your ear
耳边轻轻的啊轻点几句
When so-called angels and devils are vying for human souls
所谓的天使与魔鬼在争夺人间的这些灵魂的时候
it’s always like this
都是这样的
only able to murmur by your side and can’t actually use my own fate to interfere because when it comes to many things they all pertain to financial reform It's a necessity for development. Isn't it? That's perfectly normal.
只能在你身边耳语 还不能确实去动用自己的这些因果去干涉啊 因为很多东西来讲的话 都作为金融改革 他是发展的需要 对不对 这是很正常的
We're becoming more and more like the United States.
咱们越来越像美国了啊
I often say two things.
我经常说两句话
The U.S. and China are two relatively normal countries.
就是啊中美是两个比较正常的国家
We're becoming more and more like the United States.
咱们越来越像美国了啊
Sometimes I would say,
有时候我会说啊
Japan serves as a cautionary tale for our development.
日本是咱们的发展的前车之鉴
Sometimes we're becoming more and more like Japan.
咱们有的时候越来越像日本了
So in many ways, we are quite similar to Japan and the United States.
所以咱们其实是跟日本美国是很像的
There are a lot of similarities.
在很多地方来讲是很像的
We are also an Eastern country.
咱们又是一个东方国家
But when it comes to the economy,
但是在经济上
and in terms of culture,
在文化上
in certain aspects,
在一些啊方向上来讲
we don't really have that many differences with the United States.
其实咱们跟美国也没有多大区别啊
We are gradually moving in the same direction as the United States.
慢慢的在向美国的方向发展
Of course,
当然来讲的话
we won’t have some of the issues that the United States has,
美国的一些毛病咱们不会有
but,
但是来讲的话
the United States has also encountered some problems during its development,
美国在发展当中它也出现了一些问题
and there’s a chance we might be affected by them,
咱们有可能会被他传染到
so it’s hard to be completely clear about this matter,
所以这个东西就是没有办法说的太透的事啊
but no matter what,
但是无论怎么样
from an individual perspective,
从个人的角度出发的话
a person has to take some risks in life.
人一辈子总是要冒一些险的
So we should take the risks that can be managed
那我们就去冒那些可以被管控的风险
and avoid the ones that cannot be controlled for example, opening a coffee shop is an unmanageable risk but trying out different paths in your own life is a controllable risk
而不要去冒那些不可被管控的风险 比如开咖啡店就是一种不可被管控的风险 而自己在自己的人生当中尝试一些不同的人生道路 是一种可控的风险啊
Many people, to put it simply
其实很多的人就是怎么说呢
don't live their lives with clarity
没有把自己活得明白
they don't have a good mindset or operating system
他没有有一套很好的思维方式跟操作系统啊
and their parents haven't provided them with such a system
他的父母也没有给了他这种系统
The school system is clearly not designed to teach him to think in such a way.
学校的系统也明显不是教他这样去思考的
So, generally speaking,
所以通常来讲的话
to achieve a relatively happy state in life,
人生想获得一种比较快乐的这种状态呢
I said it's not entirely related,
我说了不是完完全全的关
from a metaphysical perspective,
从玄学角度上来讲
what books you read,
你去读什么书
what scriptures you study,
看什么经啊
how you practice,
然后怎么样练习
how you adjust your breathing,
怎么样调整你的这个气息啊
what kind of elixirs you take,
吃什么样的丹药
you can reach a certain state.
你就能达到什么样的状态
But in the real world,
而是在人世间
in the secular life,
在俗世中生活上来讲
the most important thing is to have a good grasp of money.
最重要的就是对钱的掌握是很重要的
Look at the Jews, they only think about one thing every day,
你看犹太人每天只琢磨一件事
how to use their money to make more money,
就是怎么样用自己的钱赚更多的钱
how to save money and earn compound interest.
怎么样钱省成复利
This is why Jews can rise to the top of human society,
所以犹太人能爬到人类的顶端
and there's a reason for that.
这也是有道理的
It's not about being obsessed with money, but you need to be aware of the various traps money can create, and anticipate them, and foresee them. That's the right attitude towards life. Speaking of which, when we talk about all these things in life,
并不是让你掉到钱眼儿里边儿 而是你要对钱上面会能产生各种各样的陷阱 有所估计 有所预计 这才是一个正确的人生态度 所谓的来讲的话 咱们说人生当中的所有的这些东西来讲呢
it's crucial to take risks at critical moments.
关键时刻呢还是要冒一些险的
So all these things that seem negative,
所以所有的这些看起来是负面的东西
in a certain sense,
其实在某一种程度上来讲
will eventually be transformed into something positive.
他早晚会被转化成一种比较正面的东西啊
Where does positivity come from?
正面的东西是怎么来的呢
It comes from the gradual transformation of negativity.
都是从负面的东西慢慢转化来的
Your approach to handling it is different,
你处理的方法不一样
the way you perceive it is different,
你看到他的方法不一样
the way you experience it is different,
你感受的时候不一样
you create a new experience.
你创造出来一种新的感受
So, many times,
所以很多的时候来讲
we talk about life and death,
我们就说呃生死吧
including joy, anger, sorrow, and happiness,
包括喜怒哀乐
these are states of your existence,
它本身是一种你存在的状态啊
they are situations,
它是一种处境
conditions.
一种状态
So how do you change these conditions?
所以你如何去改变这种状态呢
To put it simply,
来讲的话
this is crucial.
这个就是至关重要
The only thing we can change is our thoughts,
所以我们能改变的只有自己的思想
because when thoughts change,
因为思想改了
actions change,
行动就改了
and when actions change,
行动改了
everything changes.
一切就都变了